Xian Xu

Basic Information _

Gender: Female Birthday: 1994-5 Writer, Interdisciplinary Computational Media and Arts Researcher Research interest: Data-driven Storytelling, Cinematic Arts, Arts Education in VR and the Metaverse, and Human-Computer Interaction. I am devoted to enhancing data-driven storytelling and arts education by extending not only the disciplinary depth but also the interdisciplinary breadth.

Education Background and Research Experience _____

Cambridge University, Research Visiting Fellow

Cambridge Digital Humanities, School of Arts and Humanities, Supervised by Prof.
Caroline Bassett

Ap

Oxford University, Research Visiting Fellow

Oxford e-Research Center, Department of Engineering Science, Supervised by Prof. Min Chen

Peking University

Visualization Summer School, hosted by Prof. Xiaoru Yuan

The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology

PhD in Computational Media and Arts, Supervised by Prof. Huamin Qu

The Central Academy of Drama

MFA in Drama and Film Studies, GPA (3.92/4.0) Ranking (1/25)

The Central Academy of Drama

BS in Directing (Film and TV Producing), GPA (3.88/4.0) Ranking (1/40)

Cambridge, UK

Apr. 2023 - Jun. 2023

_ _ _ _ _

Oxford, UK

Jan. 2023 - Mar. 2023

Beijing, China

Jul. 2022

Uona Vona China

Hong Kong, China Aug. 2020 - Aug. 2023

Aug. 2020 - Aug. 202

Beijing, China Sep. 2017 - Jul. 2020

Beijing, China

Sep. 2013 - Jul. 2017

Publications _____

- [1] Xian Xu, Aoyu Wu, Leni Yang, Zheng Wei, Rong Huang, David Yip, Huamin Qu."Is It the End? Guidelines for Cinematic Endings in Data Videos" *ACM CHI 2023*. https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3544548.3580701
- [2] Xian Xu, Leni Yang, David Yip, Mingming Fan, Zheng Wei, Huamin Qu. "From 'Wow' to 'Why': Guidelines for Creating the Opening of a Data Video with Cinematic Styles" *ACM CHI 2022*. https://doi.org/10.1145/3491102.3501896
- [3] **Xian Xu**, Wai Tong, Zheng Wei, Meng Xia, Lik-Hang Lee, Huamin Qu. "Cinematography in the Metaverse: Exploring the Lighting Education on a Soundstage" *IEEE VR Poster 2023*. 10.1109/VRW58643.2023.00128
- [4] Leni Yang, Xian Xu, Xingyu Lan, Ziyan Liu, Shunan Guo, Yang Shi, Huamin Qu, Nan Cao. "A Design Space for Applying the Freytag's Pyramid Structure to Data Stories" *IEEE VIS 2021 (TVCG)*. 10.1109/TVCG.2021.3114774
- [5] Leni Yang, Aoyu Wu, Wai Tong, **Xian Xu**, Zheng Wei, Huamin Qu. "Understanding 3D data Videos: From Screens to Virtual Reality" *IEEE PacificVis* 2023. 10.1109/PacificVis56936.2023.00029
- [6] Zheng Wei*, **Xian Xu***, Lik-Hang Lee, Wai Tong, Huamin Qu, Pan Hui. "Feeling Present! From Physical to Virtual Cinematography Lighting Education with Metashadow" *ACM MM 2023 (Under Review)*.
- [7] **Xian Xu**, David Yip, Huamin Qu. "The Golden Ratio in Narrative Structure: Visualizing the Rising-Climax in Data Videos" *VIS 2023 Posters (Under Review)*.
- [8] Zheng Wei, Shan Jin, **Xian Xu**, Wai Tong, Huamin Qu, Pan Hui. "Visualizing Film Set Communication: An Interactive Interface for Collaboration in Virtual LED Production" *ISMAR 2023 (Under Review)*.
- [9] **Xian Xu**, Zelin Ye, Yuanzhe Jin, Leni Yang, Huamin Qu, Min Chen. "The Design Space of Short Technical Storytelling Videos: Through the Lens of Preview Videos in VIS Conferences" (*Under Review*).
- [10] **Xian Xu**, Wai Tong, Zheng Wei, Meng Xia, Lik-Hang Lee, Huamin Qu. "Cinematography in the Metaverse: Exploring the Lighting Education on a Soundstage" (*Under Review*).

Awards and Honors _____

Jan. 2023	Scholarship: "HKUST Overseas Research Award"	Hong Kong, China
Aug. 2020-2023	Scholarship: "Postgraduate Scholarship of HKUST"	Hong Kong, China
Jul. 2020	Honorary Title: "Excellent Postgraduate of Beijing"	Beijing, China
Dec.2019	Scholarship: "National Scholarship for PG Students"	Beijing, China
Dec.2017	Scholarship: "National Scholarship"	Beijing, China
Jul. 2017	Honorary Title: "Excellent Undergraduate of Beijing"	Beijing, China
Dec.2016	Scholarship: "National Scholarship"	Beijing, China
Jul.2016	Scholarship: "First-class Academic Award from CAD"	Beijing, China
Dec.2015	Scholarship: "National Scholarship"	Beijing, China
Jul.2015	Scholarship: "First-class Academic Award from CAD"	Beijing, China
Dec.2014	Scholarship: "National Scholarship"	Beijing, China
Jul.2014	Scholarship: "First-class Academic Award from CAD"	Beijing, China

Teaching Experience _____

IDPO 2020 Cross-disciplinary Design Thinking, HKUST	Teaching Assistant
Assist for Prof. Rong Zhang and Prof. Jinni Zhou	Feb. 2022 - Jun. 2022

CMAA 5008 Visual Communication, HKUST Assist for Prof. David Yip Sep. 2021 - Jan. 2022

The Central Academy of DramaCounselorPeking Opera, Dance Drama, Opera, and Film & TV DepartmentsSep. 2018 - Jul. 2020

Middle and Primary Schools in Beijing, ChinaDrama InstructorDrama and Film Arts EducationSep. 2017 - Jul. 2018

Work Experience and Creations _____

Data Visualization X Cinematic Arts	Writer and Designer
Four Cinematic Data Video Endings with Punctuation Marks	created in Sep. 2022
Arts Education & Technology Startup	Co-Founder
Art Mirror Network Technology Co.	founded in Jan. 2019
Our Glamorous Time	Screenwriter
TV Play of Zhejiang TV and Dragon TV in China	Broadcasted in Dec. 2018
I Like to be Independent	Writer
Bestseller in China	Published in May 2017
C'I I	α

Silent LoveScreenwriterFilm of CCTV6Created in 2016Mind ReaderScreenwriter and Director

Mind ReaderScreenwriter and DirectorSuspense-themed MicrofilmCreated in 2015

HurtScreenwriter and DirectorYouth Campus-themed MicrofilmCreated in 2014

AB Sides Screenwriter and Director

Youth Campus-themed Microfilm Created in 2014

Personal Skills _____

Languages English (Fluent), Cantonese (Native), Mandarin (Native)

Personality Optimistic, curious about new things, hardworking, and easygoing

Specialty Project management and teamwork